Finding Aid for Institute for the Study of Mental Retardation and Related Disabilities (University of Michigan) records, 1963-1983
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Institute for the Study of Mental Retardation and Related Disabilities (University of Michigan) records 1963-1983
University of Michigan. Institute for the Study of Mental Retardation and Related Disabilities.
87193 Bimu C552 2
Administrative files, conference proceedings, project proposals, research files, records, and photographs relating to continuing education conferences and workshops.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
49 linear feet
The collection was transferred to the Bentley Library in June 1983, when the Institute closed. (Donor No. 6668 )
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The collection is open to research.
In December 1963, the University of Michigan appointed a steering committee to appraise the University's role in the area of mental retardation. This committee began a comprehensive study of the University's interests and goals in this field. The subsequent report, dated June 1965, recommended the establishment of an interdisciplinary institute with a threefold purpose--to engage in research, to provide community clinical services, and to train students in the treatment of mental retardation. At the same time two laws were passed (Public Law 88-164, 1964 and Public Law 89-97, 1967) which provided potential financial support for university-affiliated centers for the treatment of the mentally retarded.
Thus in 1966, the Regents of the University of Michigan created the Institute for the Study of Mental Retardation (ISMR, later to become the Institute for the Study of Mental Retardation and Related Disabilities--ISMRRD). Administratively, ISMRRD came under the jurisdiction of the Vice-President for Academic Affairs. ISMRRD did not grant degrees, but rather cooperated with degree-programs in fifteen disciplines, including audiology, dentistry, instructional technology, nursing, nutrition, occupational therapy, pediatrics, physical therapy, psychiatry, rehabilitation counseling, social work, special education and speech pathology.
In 1982, the Budget Priorities Committee of the University of Michigan appointed a review committee to evaluate ISMRRD's program. The committee recommended that ISMRRD be closed, since it was the committee's contention that the Institute no longer excelled in any of its pursuits. Consequently ISMRRD was shut down in June 1983.
The records of the Institute consist of forty-nine linear feet of manuscripts and printed materials. The records date form 1965 to 1983. The record group is divided into four broad Series: Administrative Files (boxes 1-7), Research Files (boxes 8-18), Continuing Education (boxes 19-48), and Photographs (box 49). Of these, only the Administrative Files have been closely processed. The Administration Files are divided into several subseries, the most substantive of which are History of ISMRRD, Committees, Institute Reviews, and Projects, Proposals and Reports.
Subjects:
University of Michigan--Congresses.; Allmendinger Building (Ann Arbor, Mich.); University of Michigan. Institute for the Study of Mental Retardation and Related Disabilities.; People with mental disabilities.; Buildings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor Organ Company.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Buildings.
Genre Terms:
Motion pictures.; Videotapes.; Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Administrative Files
  - History of ISMRRD
    The History of ISMRRD subseries includes information concerning the Benz Building, where ISMRRD was housed, the ISMRRD charter, and information describing the Institute itself. There is little relating to the process of establishing ISMRRD.
    - Benz Building (Box 1)
    - Charter and Memoranda of Agreement (Box 1)
    - Description of ISMRRD (Box 1)
    - "The Institute for the Study of Mental Retardation: An Overview," 1968 (Box 1)
    - Miscellanea (Box 1)
  - Accreditation Standards
    The files in the Accreditation Standards subseries include descriptions of ISMRRD's program and administration as well as a summary of the findings of the investigation of ISMRRD.
    - Summary of Findings (Box 1)
    - Exemplary Services (Box 1)
    - Information Dissemination (Box 1)
    - Management, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Training Program (Box 1)
  - Administrative Staff
    The Administrative Staff subseries is divided into Action Steps, Agendas, Memoranda, Minutes, Personnel and Miscellanea.
    - Action Steps 1979 (Box 1)
    - Agendas 1977-1980 (Box 1)
    - Memoranda
      - 1976-September 1978 (Box 1)
      - October-December 1978 (Box 1)
      - January-April 1979 (Box 1)
      - May-September 1979 (Box 1)
      - October-December 1979 (Box 1)
      - January-April 1980 (Box 1)
      - May-November 1980 (Box 1)
    - Minutes
      - 1976-1977 (Box 1)
      - 1978 (Box 1)
      - 1979 (Box 1)
      - 1980 (Box 1)
    - Personnel (Box 1)
    - Miscellanea 1974-1980 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports
    - 1973-1974 (Box 2)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 2)
    - 1975-1976, 1976-1977 (Box 2)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 2)
    - 1978-1979 (Box 2)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 2)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 2)
  - Committees
    The subseries Committees is one of the largest in the collection. The Committees included are the Administrative Committee, Clinical Services, Committee for Behavioral Research and Training in Retardation, Committee to Study Classification and Labeling in the Area of Learning Disabilities, Core Advisory Staff Committee, Curriculum, Executive, Institute Planning, Operating Committee, Physical Therapy Discontinuance Review Committee, Planning, Preliminary Examination, Program, Program Directors Advisory Committee, Subcommittee to Study the Development of a University-Affiliated Facility for the Mentally Retarded, Training and Education, and the University Steering Committee on Mental Health. Within each committee the papers are generally divided into agendas, memoranda, and minutes, except where there is only one folder of material, in which case the arrangement is strictly chronological.
    - Administrative Committee
      - Agendas
        - 1977-1980 (Box 2)
        - 1981-1982 (Box 2)
        - Clinical Services Evaluation 1977-1981 (Box 2)
      - Fiscal Planning 1975-1981 (Box 2)
      - Memoranda
        - 1977-April 1978 (Box 2)
        - May-December 1978 (Box 2)
        - 1979-April 1980 (Box 2)
        - May-December 1980 (Box 2)
        - 1981 (Box 2)
      - Minutes
        - 1977-1979 (Box 2)
        - 1980 (Box 2)
      - Personnel (Box 2)
      - Policies (Box 2)
      - Miscellanea (Box 2)
    - Clinical Services Committee 1977-1980 (Box 2)
    - Committee for Behavioral Research and Training in Retardation 1963 (Box 2)
    - Committee to Study Classification and Labeling in the Area of Learning Disabilities
      - 1972 (Box 2)
      - 1973 (Box 2)
    - Core Advisory Staff Committee 1970-1971 (Box 2)
    - Curriculum Committee 1978 (Box 2)
    - Executive Committee
      - Agendas 1972-1981 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence 1978-1981 (Box 2)
      - Fiscal Planning 1971-1980 (Box 2)
      - Handouts
        - 1966-1970 (Box 2)
        - 1971 (Box 2)
        - 1972 (Box 2)
        - 1973 (Box 3)
      - Members 1969-1981 (Box 3)
      - Memoranda 1968-1980 (Box 3)
      - Minutes
        - 1968-1970 (Box 3)
        - 1971-1976 (Box 3)
        - 1977-1980 (Box 3)
      - Policies (Box 3)
      - Status Summaries 1971-1972 (Box 3)
      - Miscellanea (Box 3)
    - Institute Planning Committee 1967 (Box 3)
    - Operating Committee 1969 (Box 3)
    - Physical Therapy Discontinuance Review Committee 1981 (Box 3)
    - Planning Committee, "Planning Educational Facilities and Related Programs," 1968 (Box 3)
    - Policy Committee
      - 1966-1971 (Box 3)
      - 1980 (Box 3)
    - Preliminary Examination Committee 1974 (Box 3)
    - Program Committee
      - Agendas
        - 1976-1978 (Box 3)
        - 1979-1980 (Box 3)
      - Memoranda 1976-1980 (Box 3)
      - Minutes
        - 1976-September 1977 (Box 3)
        - October 1977-1978 (Box 3)
        - 1979-1981
          - Miscellanea (Box 3)
    - Program Directors Advisory Committee 1970-1972 (Box 3)
    - Subcommittee to Study the Development of a University Affiliated Facility for the Mentally Retarded
      - 1964 (Box 3)
      - 1965-1966 (Box 3)
    - Training and Education Committee
      - Memoranda 1976-1980 (Box 3)
      - Minutes 1976-1980 (Box 3)
      - Miscellanea (Box 3)
    - University Steering Committee on Mental Health -- Mental Retardation Program 1964 (Box 3)
  - Conference Proceedings
    The Conference Proceedings subseries consists of a number of printed and bound proceedings covering the year 1970-1979. It is probably not a complete set of all conferences with which ISMRRD was involved.
    - May 15-16, 1970 "The Challenge of Mental Retardation in the Community" (Box 4)
    - June 11 November 9-10, 1970 "Guidelines for the Preparation of Support Personnel" (Box 4)
    - February 10-11, 1971 "Nutrition and Mental Retardation (Box 4)
    - March 4-5, 1971 "Confrontation and Change: Community Problems of Mental Retardation and Developmental Disabilities (Box 4)
    - March 6-7, 1972 "Annual Intramural Conference' (Box 4)
    - June 2, 1972 "Advocacy for the Legal and Human Rights of the Mentally Retarded" (Box 4)
    - October, 1972 "Solutions '72: A Regional Organizational Conference to Implement the Interagency Concept ..." (Box 4)
    - June 22, 1973 "Audiological Considerations with Acoustically and Visually Impaired Children" (Box 4)
    - February 4-5, 1974 "National Information Exchange Regarding Mental Retardation and Related Disabilities" (Box 4)
    - April 8-10, 1975 "The Gerontological Aspects of Mental Retardation" (Box 4)
    - May 8-10, 1978 "Developmental Disabilities and Gerontology" (Box 4)
    - April 24-25, 1979 "University-Affiliated Facilities: A Primary Resource in Improving Services for Developmentally Disabled Persons" (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and Miscellaneous Memoranda
    The subseries Correspondence and Miscellaneous Memoranda includes information on the administration of the institute and about some research projects. The researcher should note that much correspondence may also be found within other different series.
    - 1963-1968 (Box 4)
    - 1970-1975 (Box 4)
    - 1976-1982 (Box 4)
  - Grant Information
    - 1963-1982, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Institute Review
    The Institute Review subseries documents two separate reviews of ISMRRD. One was done in 1978/79 when ISMRRD lost the financial support of the Maternal and Child Health Foundation. The second review was undertaken by the University of Michigan in 1982, and led to the closing of ISMRRD. The series is subdivided into Collected Information, Correspondence and Reports from the Review Committee, and the Institute's response (its correspondence, memoranda and publicity surrounding the decision).
    - Review Committee
      - Collected Information on ISMRRD, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Correspondence and Memoranda, 19T8-1979 (Box 4)
      - Reports (Box 4)
    - Response of ISMRRD
      - Correspondence 1982 (Box 4)
      - Executive Committee (Box 4)
      - Memoranda (Box 4)
      - Publicity
        - Newspaper Clippings (Box 4)
        - Press Releases and Statements (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous Files
    The Miscellaneous Files subseries consists of a Memoranda of Agreement, Newsletters and Pamphlets, and Planning and Policies files (which includes the ISMRRD Policy Notebook), Reorganization, School of Education, School of Nursing, and Seminars and Courses.
    - Bibliographies (Box 4)
    - Contract (proposed) with Michigan Department of Mental
      - Health 1981 (Box 4)
    - Memoranda of Agreement (Box 4)
    - Newsletters 1971-1980 (Box 4)
    - Pamphlets (Box 4)
  - Planning
    - 1964-1966 (Box 5)
    - 1969 "ISMR Planning Networks" (Box 5)
    - 1978-1979 Long Term Planning (Box 5)
    - 1980 Contingency Planning (Box 5)
  - Policies
    - General (Box 5)
    - Policy Notebook (Box 5)
  - Project Proposals and Reports
    Projects, Proposals and Reports provides some documentation of projects supported by ISMRRD. A completed project includes both the proposal and the final report. Unfortunately, most of ISMRRD's projects are not fully documented. In many cases, only the reports survive. The files are arranged alphabetically by project title (where such exists) or by broad area of concern. The projects/areas included are Abstracts, Age and Aging, Cerebral Palsy, Clinical Services, Community Living, Education, Evaluation, ISMRRD, Mental Retardation, and Training. Further material concerning projects may be found in the Research Files (boxes 8-18).
    - Abstracts 1965-1979 (Box 5)
    - Age and Aging Project
      - Art Therapy Workshops (Box 5)
      - Conference 1978-1979 (Box 5)
      - Correspondence and Memoranda
        - 1976-1977 (Box 5)
        - 1978 (Box 5)
        - 1979 (Box 5)
        - 1980-1981 (Box 5)
    - Finances, 1977-198 (Box 5)
      (including grant applications)
    - Newsletter, "Opening Doors" 1977-1979, 7 issues (Box 5)
    - Proposals-"Serving Aging and Aged Developmentally Disabled Persons"
      - September 10, 1976 (Box 5)
      - June 23, 1977 (Box 5)
      - June 26, 1978 (Box 5)
      - August 13, 1979 (Box 5)
    - Miscellanea (Box 5)
    - Cerebral Palsy Project
      - Correspondence and Memoranda
        - 1979 (Box 5)
        - 1980 (Box 5)
        - 1981-1982 (Box 5)
      - Finances 1978-1981 (Box 5)
      - Proposals "Vocational Technology Application for Adults with Cerebral Palsy"
        - May 14, 1979 (Box 5)
        - May 13, 1980 (Box 5)
      - Technical Assistance for School Personnel 1981-1982 (Box 5)
    - Clinical Services
      - Operating Manual 1976 (Box 6)
      - Reports 1970-1974 (Box 6)
    - Community Living, Services Facilitating June 8, 1973 (Box 6)
    - Education
      - Early Intervention-Project Outreach July 1976-June 1977 (Box 6)
      - July Project-ISMRRD Diagnostic Classroom July 1976 (Box 6)
      - Project KEEPS-A Demonstration Educational Program for the Severely Handicapped July 1977 (Box 6)
      - Miscellanea (Box 6)
    - Evaluation and Planning Project, 197
      - Phase I Report (Box 6)
      - Appendices
        - I-VIII (Box 6)
        - IX-XVI (Box 6)
        - XVII-XXIV (Box 6)
        - XXV-XXIX (Box 6)
    - ISMRRD
      - Proposed Program Plan 1980-1981 (Box 6)
      - Reports 1967-1977 (Box 6)
    - Mental Retardation
      - Research
        - June 30, 1965 "Task Force Report" (Box 6)
        - December 15, 1966 "Proposal for Research and/or Related Activities" (Box 6)
        - 1976 "A Proposal to the Spencer Foundation" (Box 6)
      - University-Affiliated Facilities
        - April 5 May 1965, 1968 "Preliminary Proposal for a University of Michigan Retardation Center" (Box 6)
        - June 2, 1965 "A University-Affiliated Mental Retardation Facility: Purposes and Program" (Box 6)
        - September 21, 1965 "A University-Affiliated Retardation Facility: Organization and Staff" (Box 6)
        - 1980 Research and Development Fund, correspondence (Box 6)
        - March 1981 "University-Affiliated Facilities: An Important Program for Developmental Disabilities" (Box 6)
        - May15 1981 "A Proposal ... for Continuation of University-Affiliated Facility Core Support" (Box 6)
    - Training
      - September 1977 "Mobile Diagnostic Team-End of Project Report" (Box 6)
      - September 27, 1977 "An Integrated Post-Doctoral, Pre-Professional Training Model Related to the Individual Educational Plan (I.E.P.)" (Box 6)
      - 1977-1978 "The Impact of Training: A Report of Results of the Student Feedback Survey, 1977-1978" (Box 6)
      - February 1979 "Proposal for a Rackham Certificate Program in Developmental Disabilities" (Box 6)
      - January 1980 "Final Report-Task Force on Dual Appointments" (Box 6)
      - January 18, 1980 "Five Year Plan Proposed to Maternal and Child Health Services" (Box 6)
      - August 1, 1982 "Final Report-University-Affiliated Facility Training of Professional Personnel in the Education of the Handicapped" (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous Files
    - Reorganization of ISMRRD, recommendations (Box 7)
    - School of Education 1964-1982 (Box 7)
    - School of Nursing 1976-1982 (Box 7)
    - Seminars and Courses 1971-1981 (Box 7)
  - Site Visit 1980
    The subseries, Site Visit, fairly completely documents the visit of Maternal and Child Health personnel after ISMRRD appealed this group's earlier rejection of its application for grant money. The visit took place in 1980. The subseries is divided into Correspondence, Handouts, Memoranda and Results.
    - Correspondence (Box 7)
    - Handouts (Box 7)
    - Memoranda
      - June 1980 (Box 7)
      - July 1980 (Box 7)
      - August 1980 (Box 7)
    - Results of Site Visit (Box 7)
  - Speeches
    - 1972-1981 (Box 7)
  - Summaries
    - Program Summary (Box 7)
    - Service Summaries 1977-1978 (Box 7)
    - Status Summaries 1971-1972 (Box 7)
    - "Survey of Michigan Rehabilitation Facilities: Implications for the Developmentally Disabled" (Box 7)
    - Miscellanea (Box 7)
- Research Files
  The Research Files series is arranged alphabetically by the title of the project. Researchers should not look to these files for detailed information or reports on the projects. Rather, these files contain a disparate assortment of information, correspondence and memoranda.
  - Brain Stem Evoked Response (Box 8)
  - Cerebral Palsy (Box 8)
  - Conference on Inter-University Cooperative Exchange (Box 8)
  - Control Feeling by Parents (Box 8)
  - Conversational Patterns (Box 8)
  - Cost-Benefits (Box 8)
  - Cross Modality Training (Box 8)
  - Curriculum (Box 8)
  - Dental Care (Box 9)
  - Developmental Disabilities Office (DDO) (Box 9)
  - Developmental Disabilities Office (DDO) (Box 10)
    (continued)
  - Diagnostic Classroom (Box 10)
  - Early Intervention (Box 10)
  - Early Intervention (Box 11)
  - Encyclopedia Britannica (Box 11)
  - Environmental Forces (Box 11)
  - Equipment (Box 11)
  - Evaluation of Special Education (Box 11)
  - Family Support (Box 11)
  - Gerontology (Box 11)
  - Human Fulfillment (Box 11)
  - Improving Community Services (Box 11)
  - Instructional Media Award (Box 11)
  - Intermediate School District Consortium (Box 12)
  - Interpersonal Skills Workshop (Box 12)
  - Interventive Diagnosis (Box 12)
  - Johnson Foundation Grant (Box 12)
  - Judges (Box 12)
  - Kinescope Production (Box 12)
  - Learning Disabilities (Box 12)
  - Legal Change (Box 12)
  - Litigation (Box 12)
  - Long Range Planning (Box 12)
  - Maternal and Child Health (Box 12)
  - Maternal and Child Health (Box 13)
  - Maternal and Child Health (Box 14)
  - Nutrition Teaching (Box 14)
  - Parent and Child Training Service (P.A.C.T.S.) (Box 14)
  - Pediatric Bed Utilization (Box 14)
  - Pediatric Training Program (Box 14)
  - Physical Symptomatology (Box 15)
  - Physical Therapy (Box 15)
  - Priority Fund (Box 15)
  - Public Policy (Box 15)
  - Regular Developmental Disability Information (Box 15)
  - Research Fund Proposals (Box 15)
  - Ritalin, effects of (Box 15)
  - Severely Handicapped Children (Box 15)
  - Short-Term Training and Rehabilitation (Box 15)
  - Skills Assessment Conference (Box 15)
  - Special Education (Box 16)
  - Special Education Basic Support (Box 16)
  - Special Education Component (Box 16)
  - Special Education Component (Box 17)
  - Special Education Evaluation (Box 17)
  - Special Education In-service Training (Box 17)
  - Special Education Through Simulation and Consultation (Box 17)
  - (SESAC) (Box 17)
  - SSI/DCP Manpower Planning and Development (Box 17)
  - Technical Assistance in Developmental Disabilities (TADD) (Box 18)
  - Technical Assistance to Institutional Reform Plan (Box 18)
  - University-Affiliated Facility Conference (Box 18)
  - Upper Peninsula Consortium (Box 18)
  - U.S. Service Contract (Box 18)
  - Vocational Rehabilitation (Box 18)
  - Washtenaw Intermediate School District Community Classroom (Box 18)
  - Wayne County Intermediate School District In-Service (Box 18)
- Continuing Education (Conferences, Workshops, Seminars, etc.)
  The Continuing Education series (boxes 19-48) primarily consists of materials relating to conferences, workshops and seminars either sponsored by ISMRRD or pertaining to the field of mental retardation. This series is arranged chronologically, except for boxes 46 and 47, which are broken down into Activities, Budget, Description, Forms, Policies and Procedures, and Miscellanea. These are followed by a number of ISMRRD publications, extending into box 48.
  - 1969 (Box 19)
  - 1970 (Box 19)
  - 1970/71 (Box 19)
  - 1971 (Box 19)
  - 1971/72 (Box 20)
  - 1972 (Box 20)
  - 1972/73 (Box 20)
  - 1972/73 (Box 21)
  - 1973 (Box 21)
  - 1973 (Box 22)
  - 1973/74 (Box 23)
  - 1974 (Box 23)
  - 1974 (Box 24)
  - 1974/75 (Box 24)
  - 1974/75 (Box 25)
  - 1974/75 (Box 26)
  - 1975 (Box 26)
  - 1975/76 (Box 26)
  - 1975/76 (Box 27)
  - 1976 (Box 27)
  - 1976 (Box 28)
  - 1976/77 (Box 28)
  - 1977 (Box 28)
  - 1977 (Box 29)
  - 1977 (Box 30)
  - 1977 (Box 31)
  - 1977/78 (Box 31)
  - 1977/78 (Box 32)
  - 1978 (Box 32)
  - 1978 (Box 33)
  - 1978/79 (Box 33)
  - 1978/79 (Box 34)
  - 1978/79 (Box 35)
  - 1979 (Box 35)
  - 1979/80 (Box 36)
  - 1980 (Box 36)
  - 1980 (Box 37)
  - 1980 (Box 38)
  - 1980 (Box 39)
  - 1980/81 (Box 39)
  - 1981 (Box 40)
  - 1981 (Box 41)
  - 1981/82 (Box 41)
  - 1982 (Box 41)
  - 1982 (Box 42)
  - 1982 (Box 43)
  - 1982 (Box 44)
  - 1982/83 (Box 44)
  - 1982/83 (Box 45)
  - Activities (Box 46)
  - Budget (Box 46)
  - Description (Box 46)
  - Forms (Box 46)
  - Policies and procedures (Box 47)
  - Staff (Box 47)
  - Summaries (Box 47)
  - Miscellanea (Box 47)
  - Publications (Box 47)
  - Publications (Box 48)
- Audio-visual materials
  The Audio-Visual materials series includes photographs, slide-tape presentations, and videotapes relating to the Institute’s work; also copies of historic photos of the Institute’s building, formerly the Ann Arbor Organ Works and Benz (Allmendinger) Building.
  - Photographs
    - Ann Arbor Organ Company (Box 49)
    - Ann Arbor-Views (Box 49)
    - Benz Building (Box 49)
    - "Behavior Management" meeting December 1, 1981, Prints Negatives and contact sheet (Box 49)
    - Winter Workshop 1981 negatives and contact sheets (Box 49)
    - Unidentified meeting of circa March 12 1981, negatives and contact sheets (Box 49)
    - Unidentified meeting of February 5, 1982, Prints Negatives and contact sheets (Box 49)
  - Slide-tape presentations
    - ISMRRD orientation circa 1980 [Cassette and 78 slides in carousel] (Box 49)
    - ISMRRD Clinic presentation circa 1978, Cassette and 47 slides in carousel (Box 49)
  - Videocassette
    - "Rediscovering the Community: Helping Aging, Developmentally Disabled People Benefit from Community Placement", U-matic, color (Box 49)